Finding Aid for Eskimo Art, Inc. Records, 1953-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eskimo Art, Inc. Records 1953-1994
Eskimo Art, Inc.
2 linear ft. (in 3 boxes)
Agency established by Eugene Power to provide market for Inuit art, also gallery for Inuit art. Correspondence, scrapbooks, and office files detailing the company's activities.
861010 Bp 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records came from the firm (donor no. 7312 ) in 1986 and 1996.
The collection is open for research.
Eugene Power launched Eskimo Art Inc. in 1953 as a non-profit corporation "to promote an interest and appreciation of Eskimo art in the US." Over four decades, Power's company was instrumental in bringing worldwide attention to the prints, sculptures and engravings of the Inuit Eskimos of Cape Dorset, West Baffin Island in Northern Canada. Power's son Philip Power dissolved the company shortly after his father's death in 1993.
A graduate of the University of Michigan, Power founded University Microfilms International. (UMI) in 1938 and by 1953 had become a wealthy Ann Arborite and well known philanthropist and supporter of the arts. Eskimo Art Inc. was in part the result of Power's personal relationship with James Houston, a Canadian artist and authority on printmaking. In the late 1950s, Houston both introduced and trained selected Inuit men and women in printmaking techniques based on traditional Japanese methods, with the goal that they might sell their artwork to supplement their hunting activities. Before this time, several Inuit men at Cape Dorset produced sculptures.
For more than three decades, Houston and his wife published and lectured widely, while working closely with the Canadian Handicrafts Guild, the Canadian government, and the Hudson's Bay Company to distribute Inuit artwork to the world. Eskimo Art Inc. maintained relationships with all three organizations, becoming the US distributor for Canada's Department of Northern Affairs and Natural Resources, the body charged with the supervision of Canadian Eskimo cooperatives. Houston, in turn, served on the Board of Trustees for Eskimo Art Inc., retaining a personal relationship with Power.
Eskimo Art Inc.'s main endeavor included the organization of permanent and traveling exhibitions of Inuit art in Ann Arbor and around the United States. The company worked primarily in conjunction with the Smithsonian Institution and the Canadian galleries. Eskimo Art Inc. also loaned and sold artwork to individual collectors, dealers, galleries and museums. The company sponsored events and lectures in Ann Arbor, raised money for the Inuit causes (such as for the purchase a hunting boat in 1960), and returned "a great" but untold part of its one million in sales to the Inuit people.
Several Cape Dorset artist whose work Eskimo Art Inc. distributed in the early days, became extremely well known, in particular Lucy Quinnjauak and Kenojuak Ashevak. In 1964, Canada's National Film Board produced a film on Kenojuak and in 1977, Power purchased her The Enchanted Owl, one of the most famous prints ever produced in the Canadian North, for $10,000. Inuit works which sold for $10 or $15 in the early days of the company sold for as much as $18,000 by the late 1970's.
The records of Eskimo Art, Inc. is valuable for their documentation of the firm's role in bringing awareness of Inuit art and culture to the United States, and its attempt to prevent the commercialization of this artwork. The records have been arranged into four series: Correspondence files, Informational, Scrapbooks, and Cape Dorset Annual Exhibit.
Subjects:
Art.; Eskimo art.; Artists.; Eskimo artists.; Eskimo Art, Inc.; Eskimo sculpture.; Power, Eugene B., 1905-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence files
  The Correspondence series documents Eskimo Art's activities through its personal and business relationship with James and Alma Houston, with dealers, sales representative and Canadian suppliers.
  - Canada. Department of Northern Affairs and National Resources, 1954-1964 (Box 1)
  - Gow (Col. and Mrs. Harry Gow) (sales representatives), 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Houston (James and Alma), 1953-1963, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Jaffe, Lilly Weil (dealer), 1962-1966, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Povungnetok Cooperative (supplier), 1958-1961 (Box 1)
- Informational
  The Informational series includes newspaper clippings, articles, and press and publicity materials detailing the work and activities of the firm.
  - Newspaper clippings and articles, 1961-1994 (Box 1)
  - Brochures and advertisements, 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Press releases, 1986-1993 (Box 1)
  - Publicity information, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series provides rich documentation of the introduction of Inuit artwork to the American and Canadian public and depicts changing public perceptions of Eskimo culture. The scrapbooks include articles, literature, reports, photographs of exhibits and artwork, printed reproductions, catalogs and press material.
  - Vol. 1, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 2, 1955-1962 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 3, 1962-1967 (Box 3)
  - Vol. 4, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Vol. 5, 1981-1989 (Box 2)
- Cape Dorset Annual Exhibit
  The Cape Dorset Annual Exhibit series consists of photographs of this annual exhibit for the years 1988 and 1989 as well as some printed maerial.
  - 1988 (Box 2)
  - 1989 (Box 2)